Herbert Halpert collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 5: Student research - Kentucky
  - Subseries 6: Work files/classified files (tales, legends, customs), 1948-1957, undated
    - Group 14
      - Michigan tales (Box-folder 60/17)
      - Mississippi tales (Box-folder 60/18)
      - Missouri tales (Box-folder 60/19)
      - New Jersey, New York, Ohio, Pennsylvania tales (Box-folder 60/20)
      - North Carolina tales (Box-folder 60/21)
      - Oklahoma tales (Box-folder 60/22)
      - South Carolina tales (Box-folder 60/23)
      - Texas and Western states, Idaho tales (Box-folder 60/24)
      - Ukrainian legends/Kentucky tales (Box-folder 60/25)
      - Donald M. Prince, Folklore, Winter quarter 1948 (Box-folder 60/26)
        Work file copy. The collector's original order has been maintained.
    - Group 15
      - Supernatural (miscellaneous): persons with power, water witch, dump supper, markings (Box-folder 60/27)
      - Interviews (with legends, etc.) (Box-folder 60/28)
      - Ukrainian legends (Box-folder 60/29)
      - Anecdotes - miscellaneous (Box-folder 61/1)
      - Jokes - miscellaneous (Box-folder 61/2)
      - River legends and stories (Box-folder 61/3)
      - Tales for children (Box-folder 61/4)
      - School children stories (Box-folder 61/5)
      - College tales (Box-folder 61/6)
      - Camp stories (Box-folder 61/7)
      - Mock-origin tales (Box-folder 61/8)
      - Origin legends: cosmological (Box-folder 61/9)
      - Man-in-the-moon: legend, origin (Box-folder 61/10)
      - Standard folktales or cante-fables (Box-folder 61/11)
      - Standard tales and cante-fables: animal, apologue, joke college tales, formulaic horror stories, miscellaneous (Box-folder 61/12)
      - Man in moon, place legends, origin legends (Box-folder 61/13)
      - Legendary characters, odd characters, Civil War, Indians, family and local legends, night riders, criminals (Box-folder 61/14)
      - Fools, tales with rhymes, surprising answers, trickster stories about men, women, stingy, lazy, deaf, hillbilly (Box-folder 61/15)
      - Seeming dead revive, religious, other world, devil, witch, bell witch, supernatural music (Box-folder 61/16)
      - Mountaineer, Negro stereotype, scared men, tall tale (Box-folder 61/17)
      - Naming stories (Box-folder 61/18)
      - Ghosts (to be filed) (1/2) (Box-folder 62/1)
      - Ghosts (to be filed) (2/2) (Box-folder 62/2)
      - Classical myths - modernized (Box-folder 62/3)
    - Group 16
      - Ghost/apparition as death sign (Box-folder 62/4)
      - Folk beliefs: death signs (Box-folder 62/5)
      - Seeming dead revive (Box-folder 62/6)
      - The devil at Wickliffe (Box-folder 62/7)
      - Devil child (Box-folder 62/8)
      - Devil stories: miscellaneous (Box-folder 62/9)
      - Hoodoo (Negro) (Box-folder 62/10)
      - Preacher stories (to be filed) (Box-folder 62/11)
      - Preacher and church stories (Box-folder 62/12)
      - Surprising answers or remarks (Box-folder 62/13)
      - Fool cycles (Box-folder 63/1)
      - Fools and foolish behavior (Box-folder 63/2)
      - Tales with rhymes - surprising remarks (Box-folder 63/3)
      - Surprising answers (trickster) (Box-folder 63/4)
      - Surprising answers: Johnny stories ("Uncle Jack") (Box-folder 63/5)
      - Trickster (Box-folder 63/6)
      - Trickster cycles (Box-folder 63/7)
      - Surprising action (Box-folder 63/8)
      - Behavior of women (and wives) (Box-folder 63/9)
      - Stories about men (and boys) (Box-folder 63/10)
      - Half-wit cycle and stories (Box-folder 63/11)
      - Stinginess cycle and stories (Box-folder 63/12)
      - Drunken men (Box-folder 63/13)
      - Lazy men (Box-folder 63/14)
      - Deafness or speech defect (Box-folder 63/15)
      - National or religious stereotypes (non-Negro) (Box-folder 63/16)
      - Mountaineer stories (and the like) (Box-folder 63/17)
      - Tall tales (Box-folder 63/18)
      - Tall tale cycles (Box-folder 63/19)
      - Tall tale cycle "Charlie stories" (Box-folder 63/20)
      - Riddle tales and riddles (Box-folder 63/21)
      - Sing song nonsense tales (Box-folder 63/22)
      - Formula tales: endless, circular (Box-folder 63/23)
      - Formula tales: questions (Box-folder 63/24)
      - Catch tales: pulling your leg, etc. (Box-folder 64/1)
      - Scary stories: "I've got you!" "Boo!" "You've got it!" (Box-folder 64/2)
      - Horror stories: buried alive (Box-folder 64/3)
      - Horror stories: died of fear (fork in grave) (Box-folder 64/4)
      - Horror stories (Box-folder 64/5)
      - Tales for children (Box-folder 64/6)
      - The absurd Negro: a stereotype (Box-folder 64/7)
      - Scaring a/the scared Negro (white humor) (Box-folder 64/8)
    - Group 17
      - Archive contributors, letters - Murray State College (Box-folder 64/9)
      - Kentucky - folklore contributions, gifts, etc. (Box-folder 64/10)
      - From Ray Wood file (to be filed) (Box-folder 64/11)
        Half-sheets of paper typed with children's rhymes (games, counting out, etc.), and the name of the contributor.
      - Children's material (untyped) (Box-folder 64/12)
        Handwritten rhymes, etc., on lined paper
      - Herbert Halpert: field notes (Kentucky) (Box-folder 64/13)
      - Halpert manuscript (folklore, Kentucky) - to be filed (Box-folder 64/14)
      - Rough drafts typed - to be checked (Box-folder 64/15)
      - Kentucky collectanea - to be checked before typing (Box-folder 64/16)
      - New Jersey/Kentucky archive material: to be proofread (Box-folder 64/17)
      - Tapes and records (Box-folder 64/18)
      - Childlore (check) (Box-folder 65/1)
      - Kentucky folklore: extracts (Box-folder 65/2)
      - Unusual individual: Miles Darden (Box-folder 65/3)
        Photocopy of a page from Carolina Chats, by Carl Goerch).
      - Miscellaneous, to be filed in Murray State College Kentucky collection (Box-folder 65/4)
      - To be checked and filed [miscellaneous folklore] (Box-folder 65/5)
        Various student essays and contributions.
  - Subseries 7: Classified files (folk custom, folklife), circa 1948-1957
    - Group 1
      - Tales to be typed (Box-folder 65/6)
      - List of Tennessee tales and legends (Box-folder 65/7)
      - Jog in Kentucky-Tennessee line (Box-folder 65/8)
      - Interviews (with legends, etc.) (Box-folder 65/9)
      - Storytelling and storytellers (1) (Box-folder 65/10)
      - Storytelling and storytellers (2) (Box-folder 65/11)
      - Children's book possibilities: Violetta Halpert's selections from archive (Box-folder 65/12)
    - Group 2
      - Standard folktales and cante-fables (1) (Box-folder 65/13)
      - Standard folktales and cante-fables (2) (Box-folder 65/14)
      - Standard folktales and cante-fables (3) (Box-folder 65/15)
      - Standard Aarne-Thompson tale types (Box-folder 66/1)
        "A.T." is an abbreviation for and reference to the Aarne-Thompson classification system.
      - Bible of the folk (see also "origin legends") (Box-folder 66/2)
      - Bible of the folk (plants, trees) (Box-folder 66/3)
      - Origin legends: plants (Box-folder 66/4)
      - Origin legends: people (Box-folder 66/5)
    - Group 3
      - Origin legends: cosmological (Box-folder 66/6)
      - Origin legends: animals, birds, etc. (Box-folder 66/7)
      - Animal tales (Box-folder 66/8)
      - Fables or apologues (Box-folder 66/9)
      - Naming stories (Box-folder 66/10)
      - River legends and stories (Box-folder 66/11)
      - Riddle tales and riddles (Box-folder 66/12)
      - Sing-song nonsense tales (Box-folder 66/13)
      - Formula tales: endless, circular (Box-folder 66/14)
      - Scary stories: "I've got you!" "Boo!" "You've got it!" (Box-folder 66/15)
      - Catch tales: pulling your leg, etc. (Box-folder 66/16)
      - Formula tales: questions (Box-folder 67/1)
      - Trickster (Box-folder 67/2)
    - Group 4
      - West Kentucky recordings: contents lists (Box-folder 67/3)
      - Records of T. Lamkin tapes (Murray State College) (Box-folder 67/4)
      - Harold T. Luther: special contributions (Box-folder 67/5)
      - Murray State College tapes: title lists (Box-folder 67/6)
      - Town and county histories (Box-folder 67/7)
      - Murray State College: introductory and place essays (1/2) (Box-folder 67/8)
      - Murray State College: introductory and place essays (2/2) (Box-folder 67/9)
      - Community descriptions: Kentucky (Box-folder 67/10)
      - Community descriptions: Tennessee (Box-folder 67/11)
      - Grade school folklore projects - Princeton, Kentucky (Box-folder 67/12)
      - Folk beliefes: omens (Box-folder 67/13)
      - Recordings of Thomas Lenard Lamkin (Box-folder 67/14)
      - Jane Williams: Grandpa's tales (Box-folder 67/15)
      - Folklore classification form - Murray State College (Box-folder 67/16)
    - Group 5
      - Folk beliefs and holiday customs (Box-folder 67/17)
        Student essays the collector meant to be interfiled in other folders.
      - Surprising/unusual burial requests (Box-folder 67/18)
      - Surprising answers (trickster) (Box-folder 68/1)
      - Surprising answers - Johnny stories ("Uncle Jack") (Box-folder 68/2)
      - Behavior of women (and wives) (Box-folder 68/3)
      - Stories about men (and boys) (Box-folder 68/4)
      - Lazy men (Box-folder 68/5)
      - Stinginess cycle and stories (Box-folder 68/6)
      - Surprising action (Box-folder 68/7)
      - Drunken men (Box-folder 68/8)
      - Deafness or speech defect (Box-folder 68/9)
      - Jokes/play on words (miscellaneous) (Box-folder 68/10)
      - Half-wit cycles and stories (Box-folder 68/11)
      - National or religious stereotypes (non-Negro) (Box-folder 68/12)
      - Mountaineer stories (and the like) (Box-folder 68/13)
      - Why preachers tell stories (Box-folder 68/14)
      - Preacher and church stories; children/boys; misunderstandings; surprising remarks (Box-folder 68/15)
      - Preachers and food (Box-folder 68/16)
      - Trickster cycles (Box-folder 68/17)
      - Fools and foolish behavior (Box-folder 68/18)
      - Fool cycles (Box-folder 68/19)
      - Surprising answers or remarks (Box-folder 68/20)
      - Tales with rhymes or chants - surprising remarks (Box-folder 68/21)
    - Group 6
      - Folk arts and crafts (Box-folder 68/22)
      - Folksay, miscellaneous (Box-folder 68/23)
      - Calls to animals (Box-folder 68/24)
      - Names of animals (Box-folder 68/25)
      - Names of people (Box-folder 69/1)
      - Sayings: odd or interesting (Box-folder 69/2)
      - Proverbs and proverbial sayings (Box-folder 69/3)
      - Riddles to be typed (Box-folder 69/4)
      - Locally composed folksongs (Box-folder 69/5)
      - Folktale and legend - duplicate texts (Box-folder 69/6)
      - Baby lore (Box-folder 69/7)
      - Community descriptions: Illinois (Box-folder 69/8)
      - Essays on riddles (Box-folder 69/9)
      - Folk rhymes and games with rhymes (Box-folder 69/10)
    - Group 7
      - Tennessee customs (Box-folder 69/11)
        The folder was originally titled "Miscellaneous - Tennessee and Kentucky." The header was revised to reflect the folder contents.
      - Folk customs: household (Box-folder 69/12)
      - Folk customs: other work (Box-folder 69/13)
      - Folk customs: social disapproval (Box-folder 69/14)
      - Folk customs: school (Box-folder 69/15)
      - Folk customs: hoaxes (Box-folder 69/16)
      - Crafts, house and barn types, fences, etc. (Box-folder 69/17)
        Photos in this folder are taped to paper.
      - Folk customs: holidays and customs (Box-folder 69/18)
      - Children's rhymes, English 111 (Box-folder 69/19)
      - "Speeches" and recitations, including miscellanous "poetry" (Box-folder 69/20)
      - Autograph rhymes (Box-folder 69/21)
      - Derogatory tales, names of animals, etc. (Box-folder 69/22)
      - Childlore - to be used in MAF (duplicate texts) (Box-folder 69/23)
      - Folksong (nonsense) and guessing game (Box-folder 69/24)
      - Pregnancy and childbirth (Box-folder 69/25)
      - Biographical sketches (Box-folder 69/26)
      - More riddles (Tennessee) (Box-folder 69/27)
        Work files set
      - Rhymes (general) (Box-folder 69/28)
      - Rhymes found in books (Box-folder 69/29)
      - Games without music (Box-folder 69/30)
      - Rhymes, games (Box-folder 69/31)
      - Customs (Box-folder 70/1)
      - Autograph rhymes (Box-folder 70/2)
      - Childlore - miscellanous (Box-folder 70/3)
      - Parties, games, and dances (Box-folder 70/4)
      - Omens and premonitions (Box-folder 70/5)
      - Occasions - miscellanous (Box-folder 70/6)
      - Nicknames (1) (Box-folder 70/7)
      - Nicknames (2) (Box-folder 70/8)
      - Sayings: odd or interesting (Box-folder 70/9)
      - Christian names, school days, and camp stories (Box-folder 70/10)
        No header information on the original folder
      - Cures and medicine (Box-folder 70/11)
      - Practical jokes (Box-folder 70/12)
  - Subseries 8: Work files
    Half-sheets of paper originally used as an index file/ready-reference system.
    - Preventives (1/2) (Box-folder 70/13)
    - Preventives (2/2) (Box-folder 70/14)
    - Pregnancy /infancy (Kentucky, Tennessee) (Box-folder 70/15)
    - Pregnancy (Box-folder 70/16)
    - Childbirth (Box-folder 70/17)
    - Beliefs about infants (1/2) (Box-folder 71/1)
    - Beliefs about infants (2/2) (Box-folder 71/2)
    - Death (Box-folder 71/3)
    - Omens and premonitions (Box-folder 71/4)
    - Death taboos (Box-folder 71/5)
    - Breaks in skin, wounds/cuts, bites (Box-folder 71/6)
    - Wart cures (Box-folder 71/7)
    - Respiratory (Box-folder 71/8)
    - Stomach ailments (Box-folder 71/9)
    - Worms (Box-folder 71/10)
    - Chills and fever, goiter (Box-folder 71/11)
    - Head (eyes, ears, nose) (Box-folder 71/12)
    - Rheumatism, cramps, pains, etc. (Box-folder 71/13)
    - Good and bad luck (1/7) (Box-folder 72/1)
      According to the accompanying note, the slips are "from the Kentucky-Tennesse collection that have items from other states and some (apparantly) duplicate slips."
    - Good and bad luck (2/7) (Box-folder 72/2)
      See the note for Box-Folder 54/3.
    - Good and bad luck (3/7) (Box-folder 72/3)
    - Good and bad luck (4/7) (Box-folder 72/4)
    - Good and bad luck (5/7) (Box-folder 72/5)
    - Good and bad luck (6/7) (Box-folder 72/6)
    - Good and bad luck (7/7) (Box-folder 72/7)
    - Friendship (Box-folder 72/8)
    - Weather (1/4) (Box-folder 72/9)
    - Weather (2/4) (Box-folder 72/10)
    - Weather (3/4) (Box-folder 73/1)
    - Weather (4/4) (Box-folder 73/2)
    - Weather, pregnancy and childbirth, riddles, etc. (Box-folder 73/3)
      The original folder header indicates these materials were to be filed, and were sourced from Kentucky and Tenessee.
    - Beliefs (duplicate set/slips) (1/6) (Box-folder 73/4)
    - Beliefs (duplicate set/slips) (2/6) (Box-folder 73/5)
    - Beliefs (duplicate set/slips) (3/6) (Box-folder 73/6)
    - Beliefs (duplicate set/slips) (4/6) (Box-folder 73/7)
    - Beliefs (duplicate set/slips) (5/6) (Box-folder 73/8)
    - Beliefs (duplicate set/slips) (6/6) (Box-folder 73/9)
    - Times for planting and other farm-related activities (1/2) (Box-folder 73/10)
      This group of slips was originally titled "Times for planting."
    - Times for planting and other farm-related activities (2/2) (Box-folder 74/1)
    - Wishing (1/2) (Box-folder 74/2)
    - Wishing (2/2) (Box-folder 74/3)
    - Death (Box-folder 74/4)
    - Riddles, counting, rhymes, games, jumping rope (Box-folder 74/5)
    - Farm and garden, planting and crops (Box-folder 74/6)
    - Trees and flowers (wood) (Box-folder 74/7)
    - Livestock and other animals (Box-folder 74/8)
    - Cats and rabbits (Box-folder 74/9)
    - Dogs, horses, etc. (Box-folder 74/10)
    - Amphibians and insects (Box-folder 74/11)
    - Birds; fowl (Box-folder 74/12)
    - Sports and games (Box-folder 75/1)
    - Fishing (Box-folder 75/2)
    - The human body (1/2) (Box-folder 75/3)
    - The human body (2/2) (Box-folder 75/4)
    - Things worn, carried, possessed (Box-folder 75/5)
    - Friendship (Box-folder 75/6)
    - Household (domestic economy) (Box-folder 75/7)
    - Foods (Box-folder 75/8)
    - Furniture (chairs, mirrors, pictures, etc.) (Box-folder 75/9)
    - Taboo (days of the week) (Box-folder 75/10)
    - Taboo (farm tools) (Box-folder 75/11)
    - Taboo (umbrella) (Box-folder 75/12)
    - Taboo (out different door) (Box-folder 75/13)
    - Taboo: turning back (counter-charms) (Box-folder 75/14)
    - At table; in the kitchen (Box-folder 75/15)
    - Holiday foods (Box-folder 75/16)
    - Salt (Box-folder 75/17)
    - Housekeeping (Box-folder 75/18)
    - Sweeping/brooms (Box-folder 75/19)
    - Sleeping/bed (Box-folder 75/20)
    - Pin: omen (good and bad) (Box-folder 76/1)
    - Company coming (Box-folder 76/2)
    - Holidays (Box-folder 76/3)
    - Magic/supernatural (Box-folder 76/4)
    - Bad luck (general) (Box-folder 76/5)
    - Moon (Box-folder 76/6)
    - Dreams (Box-folder 76/7)
    - Hoaxes and practical jokes (Box-folder 76/8)
    - Parties, games, and dances (Box-folder 76/9)
    - Childlore (Box-folder 76/10)
    - Bad luck (omen) (Box-folder 76/11)
    - Weather (Box-folder 76/12)
    - Dry/clear/fair weather (Box-folder 76/13)
    - Cold weather (Box-folder 76/14)
    - Rain (1/2) (Box-folder 76/15)
    - Rain (2/2) (Box-folder 76/16)
    - Snow (Box-folder 77/1)
    - Frost (Box-folder 77/2)
    - Weather (miscellaneous) (Box-folder 77/3)
    - Wishing (1/2) (Box-folder 77/4)
    - Wishing (2/2) (Box-folder 77/5)
    - Courting and marriage (Box-folder 77/6)
    - Medicine/cures (Box-folder 77/7)
    - Miscellaneous from Kentucky and Tennessee (1/2) (Box-folder 77/8)
    - Miscellaneous from Kentucky and Tennessee (2/2) (Box-folder 77/9)
    - Dreams (Box-folder 77/10)